Inventory of the Jefferson H. Clark Collection 1914-2000
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Special Collections, Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Jefferson H. Clark Collection 1914-2000
Special Collections Research Center
01/Mss. Acc. 2009.191
1.00
Clark, Jefferson H., b. 1890; Shade, Mary Clark, 1928-2009 arrangement
Administrative Information
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open to all researchers.
Acquisition Information
The materials were acquired by Special Collections Research Center on 04/26/2009.
Custodial History
Seller obtained collection from Mary Clark Shade's husband, Jefferson H. Clark's son-in-law.
Biographical Note
Information about this individual or organization may be available in the Special Collections Research Center Wiki: http://scrc.swem.wm.edu/wiki/index.php/Jefferson H. Clark.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of the papers of Jefferson H. Clark, a Philadelphia, Pennsylvania physician, who was a field surgeon in France during World War I, and of the research papers of his daughter Mary Clark Shade (1928-2009), who was working on a book documenting her father's WWI duty. Mary Clark Shade's research papers include index cards, notes, photographs, postcards, photocopies of articles, and related material. Jefferson H. Clark's papers include diaries, an officer's record book, correspondence, military orders and records, maps (one of which is labeled 'trench map'), photographs, dictionary, his helmet and embroidered helmet bag, a ration tin and a surgical kit. Images of Mr. Clark's helmet: http://www.flickr.com/photos/scrc/3513839526/ and http://www.flickr.com/photos/scrc/3513031099/ Embroidered helmet handbag: http://www.flickr.com/photos/scrc/3513839718/ and http://www.flickr.com/photos/scrc/3513030861/ Surgical instruments: http://www.flickr.com/photos/scrc/3513839304/ Diary http://www.flickr.com/photos/scrc/3513031319/ can be found on the SCRC's Flickr page.
Arrangement of Materials
This collection is arranged into two series: Series 1: Jefferson H. Clark; and Series 2: Mary Clark Shade Book Research.
Additional Information
Separated Materials
All artifacts are housed and described in the Manuscripts Artifact Collection.
Index Terms
This Collection is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Genre/Form of Material:
Diaries; Letters (correspondence); Maps.; Newspapers; Orders (military records); Photographs; Research notes
Occupation:
United States. Army--Surgeons.
Topical Term:
Helmets; Postcards.; Surgical instruments and apparatus; Women authors, American--20th century.; World War, 1914-1918--France; World War, 1914-1918--France--Personal narratives; World War, 1914-1918--France--Pictoral works; World War, 1914-1918--Medical care--France
Detailed Description of the Collection
- Jefferson H. Clark, 1916-1920; id66780
  - id66782 (Box 1)
    - Personal Papers, 1916-1920; id66784 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - French/English Dictionary and Pocket-Sized Soldier's Diary, 1916-1920; id66785 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Le Miroir Newspaper, 1916-1918; id66786 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Military Maps of France and Belgium, 1916-1920; id66787 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Photographs, 1916-1920; id66788 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Diary, 1917-1918; id66789 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Promotion to First Lieutenant Certificate, May 19, 1917; id66790
- Mary Clark Shade Book Research, 1914-2000; id66798
  - id66800 (Box 2)
    - Travel Research, 1980-2000; id66802 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Research notes and clippings, 1980-2000; id66803 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Photographs, 1980-2000; id66804 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Photographs, 1980-2000; id67044 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Photocopies and Clippings from American and European Newspapers, 1914-1919, 1983-1992; id66805 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Index cards, 1980-2000; id66806 (Box 3)
  - Index cards, 1980-2000; id66807 (Box 4)